# Alan Guedes — C.V.

London – UK

## **Shorbio**

I am Computer Scientist (PhD & Postdoc), and my career can be seen threefold. In research, I have contributed to projects on Multimedia & Machine Learning (ML) and participated in technical committees (ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia). I am currently interested in non-Euclidean ML methods for the next generation of immersive and multimedia systems. Second, I have added value to the industry by contributing to applied projects and standards at industry forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum). While in teaching, I acted as an undergrad lecturer and postgraduate assistant. Also, I got involved in public engagement and promoted student interests in social impact.

# **Experiences**

Work.....

#### UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream, funded by EPSRC, to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

#### PUC-Rio. TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR, funded by RNP and Microsoft to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML Anti-Money Laundry, funded by BTG Bank, to detect financial transcations risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP, funded by RNP, to develipe a blockchain-based system for academic certificates;

### Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer

2012-2012

Highlights: multiple awarded social impact project.

- Brasil4D, funded by World Bank, design a transmission of social impact TV content to low-income families. Its results were published at a public report

Education

#### **PUC-Rio**

PhD. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga reference implementation, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses to TV manufacturers;
- From SBTVD Conformance Test Suite for TV manufacturers

#### **UFPB**

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis used in the awarded World Bank funded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- GingaAppStore, funded by RNP, to design broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI, funded by RNP, to design agile methods for TV applications development;

#### IIFDR

BSc. in Computer Science. Final report on Component-based architecture for TV middleware 2005–2009

- Ginga CDN, funded by RNP, to develop reusable TV middleware components.
- Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

## Research

## Publications...

Google Scholar shows >50 published papers, >100 citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some selected publications.

Elsevier Book Chapter		2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.	2016	2022
Springer Journal on Multimedia Tools and Applications. IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).	2016,	2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021,		
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.		2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.		2019
Service on Committees.		2013
ACM SIG Multimedia		
Reviwer and chairing	2020-1	today
<ul> <li>Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023)</li> <li>Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022)</li> <li>Immersive Experiences (ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022)</li> <li>QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023)</li> <li>Web and Mulimedia Committee of Brazilian Computing Society (SBC)</li> <li>Reviwer and chairing</li> </ul>	2017-1	today
<u>c</u>		-
<ul> <li>WebMedia conference: Steering Committee (2019-today), reviewer (2013-today), chair of workshop (2018), chair of Demos Workshop (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop Springer</li> </ul>		
Reviewer	2022-1	today
<ul> <li>Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023)</li> <li>Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022)</li> <li>Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD)</li> </ul>		
Academic member at Techincal Module contributing to TV middleware standards	2017-	-2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Academic member at $SG-16/Q13$ contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-	-2021
Teaching		
UCL		
Co-supervise undergrad engineering projects.	2022-1	today
SBC WebMedia	2010	2022
Organizer of students workshop to promote Social Impact research.	2018-	-2022
PUC-Rio Invited Lecture on ML for Multimedia to postgrad students (>30)		2019
Lecturer on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (>30).		2013
Japan International Cooperation Agency		2010
Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals(>30 RNP ESR	0)	2012
Lecturer on Linux Administration to IT professionals (>30)		2011
UFPB		
Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students	(>15)	2010
Tutor on Analysis and design of Algorithms to undergrad students $(>30)$ .		2008
Funding & Awards		
-		
Funding & Awards  Aproved Funding  Approved as PI in VideoMR project, funded by RNP and Microsoft.		2019
Aproved Funding.		
Aproved Funding.  Approved as PI in VideoMR project, funded by RNP and Microsoft.		2019

- SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng (2017, 2019)
- SIGHI Gary Marsden Travel Award for IMX (2022)

South America TV associations

2013-2014

- SET Conference award on Best TV interactivity solution for Brasil4D project
- Honorable metion on Innovation and Creativity for Brasil4D project
- FRIDA Innovative TV technological solutions award for Brasil4D project

#### ITI

IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore

2012

# **Skills**

Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writting.

Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills.

Programing: Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Dcoker.

Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, team-work, lead-by-example attitudes.

Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent).

Training

UCL

Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding. 2022-2023

Nature

Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review. 2022-2023

ITU

ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups

2023

# References

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. PhD supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $-\ Roberto\ Azevedo,\ roberto. azevedo @disneyre search.com.\ Tele Midia\ collaborator.$